Pengyu Cheng □ pengyu.cheng@duke.edu • • linear95.github.io

Research Interests

I am a third-year Ph.D. student in the Department of Electric and Computer Engineering at Duke University. My research interests focus on Bayesian deep learning, geometric deep learning, interpretable machine learning and their applications in natural language processing, speech processing, and multi-modality.

Education

Duke University 08/2017–Present

Ph.D. Student, Electrical and Computer Engineering

Tsinghua University 08/2013–07/2017

B.S., Mathematics and Statistics

Experience

Information Initiative at Duke (iiD)

08/2017-Present

Research Assistant Adviser: Lawrence Carin

Bayesian deep learning, geometric deep learning, and their applications in natural language processing.

NEC Laboratories America, Inc.

05/2019-08/2019

Research Internship Adviser: Martin Rengiang Min

Disentangled text generation learning from an information-theoretic perspective.

Tsinghua Intelligent Vision Group (IVG)

03/2016-07/2016

Student Researcher Adviser: Jiwen Lu

Deep metric learning for person re-identification based on sequential frames information.

Student Research Program at Tsinghua

11/2015-05/2017

Student Researcher Adviser: Xuegong Zhang

Non-parametric k-sample tests with statistics based on local maximum energy distance.

Beijing Sogou Information Service Co., Ltd.

08/2014-09/2014

Research Internship

Mentor: Mao Wang

Polygonal line-like city road data smoothing via Spline Interpolation; road data compressing via Douglas-Peucker algorithm.

Publications

- P. Cheng, W. Hao, S. Dai, J. Liu, Z. Gan, and L. Carin, "CLUB: A Contrastive Log-ratio Upper Bound of Mutual Information", International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2020
- P. Cheng, M. Min, D. Shen, C. Malon, Y. Zhang, Y. Li and L. Carin, "Improving Disentangled Text Representation Learning with Information-Theoretic Guidance", Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), 2020
- o **P. Cheng**, Y. Li, X. Zhang, L. Chen, D. Carlson, L. Carin, "Dynamic Embedding on Textual Networks via a Gaussian Process", American Association of Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), 2020 Oral
- P. Cheng *, D. Shen *, D. Sundararaman, X. Zhang, Q. Yang, M. Tang, A. Celikyilmaz, and L. Carin, "Learning Compressed Sentence Representations for On-Device Text Processing", Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), 2019 Oral

- o L. Chen, G. Wang, C. Tao, D. Shen, **P. Cheng**, X. Zhang, W. Wang, Y. Zhang, and L. Carin, "Improving Textual Network Embedding with Global Attention via Optimal Transport", Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), 2019
- o C. Liu, J. Zhuo, **P. Cheng**, R. Zhang, J. Zhu, and L. Carin, "Understand and Accelerate Particle-based Variational Inference", International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2019
- o **P. Cheng**, C. Liu, C. Li, D. Shen, H. Ricardo, and L. Carin, "Straight-Through Estimator as Projected Wasserstein Gradient Flow", Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) Workshop, 2018 Spotlight

Academic Activities

| o Conference reviewer/PC member for NeurIPS 2020 | 05/2020 |
|---|---------|
| o Conference reviewer/PC member for ICML 2020 | 02/2020 |
| o Oral Presentation at AAAI 2020 | 02/2020 |
| o Teaching assistant for <i>Probabilistic Machine Learning</i> , Instructor: Sayan Mukherjee, Ph.D. | 01/2020 |
| o Conference reviewer/PC member for AAAI 2020 | 09/2019 |
| o Teaching assistant for <i>Introduction to Deep Learning</i> , Instructor: Vahid Tarokh, Ph.D. | 09/2019 |
| o Oral Presentation at ACL 2019 | 07/2019 |
| o Spotlight talk at NeurIPS 2019 Bayesian Deep Learning workshop | 12/2018 |
| | |

Awards

| o Fellowship of Electrical and Computer Engineering at Duke | 08/2017 |
|--|---------|
| o First in Duke-Tsinghua Machine Learning Summer School (1/112) | 08/2017 |
| o Academic Excellence Award of Tsinghua University (top 30%) | 10/2014 |
| o Top 5 in the 18-th "Sogou Cup" Artificial Intelligence Programming Contest (5/200) | 04/2014 |
| o Silver medal in the 28-th Chinese Mathematical Olympiad (CMO) | 01/2013 |
| o First Prize in Chinese National Olympiad in Informatics in Provinces (NOIP) | 11/2012 |

Technical Strengths

Computer Languages: Python (Tensorflow, Pytorch), R, C/C++

Software & Tools: LaTeX, Emacs, Mathematica, MATLAB, Excel, Markdown

Graduate Courses

Theoretical: Random Signals and Noise; Information Theory; Multivariate Statistical Analysis; Stochastic Processes; Compressed Sensing;

Engineering: Programming, Data Structure and Algorithms in C++; Pattern Recognition; Machine Learning; Text Data Analysis;